Finding Aid for Michigan Association for Children with Emotional Disorders Records, 1957-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Association for Children with Emotional Disorders Records 1957-1991, 1957-1980
Michigan Association for Children with Emotional Disorders.
3.5 linear feet
0447 Bf 2
Organization established to provide support to families having children with emotional disorders and to educate the public about children with emotional disorders and the kinds of services they require. Organizational records include annual meeting files and subject files; also materials from chapters throughout the state.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor No. 9402 ) was received from the Association in November 2003.
The record group is open to research.
Founded in 1957 by parents, mental health professionals, and educators who recognized the need for citizen action on behalf of mentally ill children and their families, the Michigan Association for Children with Emotional Disorders (MACED) has continued for over 40 years to promote change at a grassroots level. The organization's mission is "to help families find educational, mental health, and other services for children with emotional disorders as well as to encourage and enhance the public's understanding and support of these children, their families and the services they desperately need."
MACED advocates for individual children and lobbies to influence state lawmakers, emphasizing active parent involvement in the organization. Parents, as leaders, bring personal experiences and add a sense of urgency to the organization's efforts. Their contribution, coupled with the active participation of professional workers, has enabled the organization to affect change over the years. In its early years, the organization worked to create separate psychiatric facilities for children, who were at that time treated in adult facilities. In the 1990s, MACED sued the Michigan Department of Mental Health and 12 community mental health boards to prevent the state from continuing to close long-term children's psychiatric facilities or to reduce their staff. In 2002, MACED established a juvenile justice initiative to provide direct services to children confronted with juvenile charges and to develop systematic approaches for diverting children from the criminal system and into the mental health system.
Originally named the Michigan Association for Emotionally Disturbed Children, MACED is organized into a number of chapters throughout the state, with a central statewide office based in Southfield and a regional office in Kalamazoo. Sam Davis served as Executive Director from 1960 to 1969, and the current Executive Director is Susan McParland, serving since February 2001. MACED has been and currently remains a United Way agency, also receiving funding from private donations.
The Michigan Association for Children with Emotional Disorders Records include newsletters, minutes, flyers, programs, and correspondence related to the functioning of both the state organization as well as local chapters. The Michigan Association for Children with Emotional Disorders Records (3.5 linear feet) date from 1958 to 1991, but the bulk of the material covers the period 1958 to 1980. The collection is arranged in two series: State Organizational Materials and Chapter Materials.
Subjects:
Michigan Association for Children with Emotional Disorders.; Emotional problems of children--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Children with mental disabilities--Michigan--Societies, etc.
- State Organizational Materials
  The series State Organizational Materials, 1959-1991 (1.25 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically and contains records of the organization's state-wide annual meetings, budget and financial reports, newsletters, and correspondence. The researcher may find the Annual Meeting files to be useful in gauging topics that emerged as priorities and concerns for the organization. Also of interest are the financial materials, particularly those prepared for the United Way of Michigan, as they include narratives that describe the activities of the organization and its strategic plan for the upcoming years. While the run of the organization's Newsletter is scattered, it also contains details of state and local activities, articles on state mental health news, and information about officers of the association, amongst other topics.
  - Annual Meetings 1959-1973, 1975-1988, 26 folders (Box 1)
    (1972 folder includes audio cassette)
  - Board of Directors Meetings 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - By-Laws, Officers, etc. 1980, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1965-1985 (Box 1)
  - Directors of In-Patient Children's and Adolescent Services 1972-1980 (Box 1)
  - Edith Wigder Award 1973-1978 (Box 1)
  - Emergency Psychiatric Facilities for Children
    - Articles of Incorporation and Minutes 1959-1964 (Box 1)
  - Emergency Services Division
    - Correspondence 1960-1967 (Box 1)
  - Fee Charging (Public Act 335 of 1965) 1965-1975 (Box 1)
  - Financial Materials
    - Financial Reporting Manual for Chapter Treasurers 1989 (Box 1)
    - Financial Reports 1967, 1973-1990, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - United Way of Michigan, Budget and Allocation Materials 1980-1991, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Fundraising 1973 (Box 2)
  - Holiday Cards (Box 2)
  - Leadership Conferences 1971, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Legal Affairs Committee 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Membership Directory 1979 (Box 2)
  - Publications
    - "A Parents' Guide to the EPPC" (Educational Planning and Placement Committee) 1977 (Box 2)
    - "Membership Memo," 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - "Newsletter," 1960-1977 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - "Questions and Answers about Disturbed Children," 1 1966 undated (Box 2)
  - Regional Offices
    - Kalamazoo 1983-1985 (Box 2)
  - Studies
    - Research Study on the Crisis Situation Facing Emotionally Disturbed Children in Michigan 1966 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Studies on Emotional and Learning Problems (Box 2)
  - Task Force on Emotionally Disturbed Children, ca. 1964 (Box 2)
  - Task Force on Special Education 1977 (Box 2)
  - Working Conference on Child and Adolescent Treatment Services 1978-1979 (Box 2)
- Chapter Materials
  The series Chapter Materials, 1957-1989 (2.25 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically by chapter. The files include a range of correspondence, programs, minutes, and newsletters that document the activities of the chapter, and in some instances, the interaction of the chapter with the state organization and with other chapters. The Greater Detroit Chapter is documented in the greatest depth within the collection, and the files include records relating to the chapter's funding of scholarships for students and campers, as well as its participation as a United Foundation organization. The Chapter Materials are useful in learning more about local issues and concerns in the area of children's mental health and in assessing local programming and response.
  - Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti 1960-1965 (Box 2)
  - Bay City 1964-1968 (Box 2)
  - Genesee 1967-1977 (Box 2)
  - Grand Rapids 1970-1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Greater Detroit
    - Awards (Box 2)
    - Board of Directors (Box 2)
    - Carousel Ball 1961-1963, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Child Placement Fund 1969-1972 (Box 2)
    - General 1958-1989, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Program Enrichment Grants 1962-1971, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Scholarship-Training Stipends 1963-1975 (Box 2)
    - Summer Recreation Program 1976-1979 (Box 2)
    - United Community Services Funding (Box 2)
    - United Foundation Participation 1963-1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Women's Division 1962-1965 (Box 2)
  - Hawthorn-Northville 1957-1984, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Jackson 1960-1963 (Box 3)
  - Kalamazoo 1961-1967, 1977-1979, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Lansing Area 1960-1988, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Macomb County 1966-1967, 1975-1977, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Menominee-Delta-Schoolcraft 1986-1988 (Box 3)
  - Midland 1962-1970, 1980, 1984-1986, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Muskegon Area 1975-1978, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - Northwest Michigan 1984-1988 (Box 3)
  - Oakland County 1966-1988, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Otsego County 1984-1988 (Box 3)
  - Parents Guild 1962-1975 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Redford 1973-1977 (Box 3)
  - Rochester 1969-1975, 1983-1986 (Box 3)
  - Saginaw 1962-1967 (Box 3)
  - St. Clair County 1976-1986 (Box 4)
  - Shiawassee 1985-1988 (Box 4)
  - Tri-County 1959-1962 (Box 4)
  - Upper Peninsula 1977-1985 (Box 4)
  - Washtenaw 1966-1988, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Western Wayne/Redford 1963-1972, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Wexford-Missaukee 1987-1988 (Box 4)